David DUNEAU, PhD

University Toulouse, Laboratory *Evolution Diversité Biologique* (France) & Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência (Portugal)

🙎 : david.duneau@gmail.com

Languages: French (native); English (fluent); Portuguese (basic); R (fluent)

Research interests

My research asks why individuals vary in their responses to environmental challenges with a focus on the challenges imposed by parasites. I test evolutionary and ecological concepts in model invertebrates by integrating experimental approaches such as functional genetics with statistical modelling, genomics (GWAS), and transcriptomics.

- Host-parasite interaction co-evolution sexual dimorphism phenotypic plasticity
 - genetic basis of quantitative traits within-host dynamics
 - bacteria *Drosophila*

Research positions

01/01/2020 to 31/10/2020 & 01/01/2021 to 30/06/2021:

Independent researcher, Laboratoire International Associé programme

Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência, Portugal & University Toulouse 3, France.

01/04/2015 to 31/10/2017 & 01/09/2019 to 31/10/2019:

Senior post-doctoral research associate

Lab. Evolution and Biological Diversity (EDB) University Toulouse 3.

01/11/2011 - 22/12/2014:

SNSF post-doctoral research associate

Lazzaro Lab, Cornell University, USA.

Career break

01/11/2017 to 31/08/2019: ~2 years parental leave (1 child now 6 years old)

Education

2007 – 23/09/2011: **PhD student in Evolutionary parasitology** Basel Univ. (CH) (Sept 23, 2011) *'Evolutionary and proximate mechanisms shaping host-parasite interactions: The case of* Daphnia magna *and its natural bacterial parasite* Pasteuria ramosa.'

2004 - 2006: Masters in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Montpellier Univ. (FR)

2001 - 2004: Bachelor of Science in Organismal Biology, Montpellier Univ. (FR)

Funding

- Sponsored fellowships and postdoc funding (278K€)
 - o Fellowship from Gulbenkian Foundation in Lisbon (2020 & 2021; 30K€)
 - o Post-doctoral 'Prestigious and Marie Curie Fellowship' (2017; 51K€)
 - o Post-doctoral fellowship from LabEx TULIP (2015; 112K€)
 - o Post-doctoral fellowship from Swiss NSF (2011 & 2013; 76K€)

o Fellowship from the Emilia Guggenheim-Schnurr foundation in Basel (2009; 9K€)

Grants

- o PI David Duneau and Lucie Zinger: Disentangling the factors shaping gut microbiota diversity across arthropod predators (EDB Toulouse Univ. funded by LabEx CEBA; 2016; 20K€)
- o PI Jean-Baptiste Ferdy (Duneau D. co-PI, 15%-time allocation): Pathogens adaptation to their host's microbiome (EDB Toulouse Univ., funded by "New frontiers" LabEx TULIP project; 2016; 82K€)
- o PI Patrícia Beldade (Duneau D. co-PI, 20%-time allocation): Adaptive Developmental Plasticity: genetic and environmental components of phenotypic variation (FCT Portugal; 2016; 192K€)
- <u>5 Travel grants</u> to attend conferences.

Main scientific accomplishments

My research has contributed to:

- **Parasite manipulating host behaviour** can escape from the predators (frog) of their host (Ponton et al. Nature 2006).
- o Determining the mechanism responsible for the **coevolution between a host and its parasite** (Duneau *et al.* BMC Biol. 2011).
- o Describing **sexual dimorphism in responses to infections** in *Drosophila* (Belmonte *et al.* Front. Imm. 2020) and uncovering **mechanisms driving dimorphism** (Duneau *et al.* BMC Biol. 2017).
- o Proposing (Duneau & Ebert PLoS Biol. 2012), and demonstrating (Duneau *et al.* BMC Biol. 2012), that **parasites can adapt specifically to the sex of the host** they encounter the most often.
- o Understanding the link between **within-host dynamics and infection outcome** (Duneau *et al.* eLife 2017, invited review in Current Opinion Insect Science 2022).
- o Characterising the **genetic basis of insecticide resistance** (Duneau *et al.* G3 2018) and **phenotypic plasticity** (Lafuente *et al.* PLoS Gen. 2018, Bonfini *et al.* eLife 2021).
- Showing that the distinct steps of infection impose trade-offs to bacterial within-host evolution (Faucher *et al.* mBio 2020).
- Showing that cancer can increase the risk of being predated (Duneau et al. BioRxiv 2020).

Academic leadership

• Reviewer for 20 Journals

■ Animal Behaviour ■ Biology Letters ■ BMC Biology ■ BMC ecology ■ BMC Evolutionary Biology ■ Coevolution ■ Ecology and Evolution ■ Evolution ■ Epidemiology and Infection ■ Heredity ■ Invertebrate Biology ■ Invertebrate Survival Journal ■ Nature Communications ■ Oecologia ■ Oikos ■ Phil. Transactions of the Royal Society ■ PLoS ONE ■ PNAS ■ Proceedings of the Royal Society B ■ Journal of Animal Ecology.

• Reviewer for 4 funding agencies

Sigma Xi awards research grants program • National Commission for Scientific and Technological Research of Chile • National Fund for Scientific Research of Belgium (NFWO) • European Research Council (ERC).

• Thesis committee and jury

- Examiner for Pinaud S at Univ. Perpignan (France) supervised by Gourbal B (2018)
- o Thesis committee Hanson M at EPFL (Switzerland) supervised by Lemaitre B (2018)

• Administrative & organisational roles

- Part of the scientific committee of the French Network "Réseau Ecologie des Interactions Durables" (REID) (2020-current).
- Organisation of the National meeting of the French Network "Réseau Ecologie des Interactions Durables" (REID) (2017, Museum natural history of Toulouse).
- o Organisation of departmental seminars (2015 to 2017, University of Toulouse 3)
- Organisation of seminars aiming to present experiments or analyses before they were performed.
 (From fall 2009 to spring 2011, Zoological Institute Basel)

Teaching

Active learning grounded in evidence-based techniques of teaching

- Evaluation in "Evolutionary biology and genetics" (2017 & 2018) Level: 3rd year undergraduate, University of Toulouse 3. We used a <u>role play</u> method to evaluate their understanding of concepts in evolutionary biology (example of questions: "What is death in an evolutionary biology context?", "What is the cost of sex?").
- Teaching assistant, practical in *Ecological and Evolutionary Genetics* (2009 and 2010). Level: Masters student, University of Basel. I developed exercises based on real examples and employed a "<u>think pair share</u>" method, where students *think* for themselves, exchange with their neighbour (*pair*) and *share* with the class.
- Teaching of *Introduction to biology* (2009). Level: group of ~10 1st year undergraduates, University of Basel. I put the students at the centre of the teaching by asking them to respond to a set of <u>concept inventory questions</u> before the lecture (at home) and, after having established the students who knew the answer, I asked those students <u>to participate in the teaching</u> by explaining concepts to their classmate.

• Conventional

- Numerous and continual participation in mock panels and presentation critique for PhD students approaching their defence.
- o Invited lecture on host-parasite coevolution (2017). Level: high school teachers.
- o Summer school LabEx TULIP (2015) on Integrative Ecology and Biology "Biological interactions from genes to ecosystems". Level: from 4th year undergraduates to Postdoc.
- o Departmental workshop on statistical analysis of experimental data. Level: Postgraduates (2014).
- Tutor in student scientific projects (2008 to 2010). Level: 3rd year undergraduate, University of Basel.
- o Teaching assistant, *practical of Animal Biology (Embryology)* with Prof. Louis Du Pasquier (2009). Level: 3rd year undergraduates, University of Basel.
- o Teaching assistant, *practical of Animal Biology (Entomology)* with Prof. Dieter Ebert (2008). Level: 3rd year undergraduates, University of Basel

Student supervision (1 thesis as co-supervisor, 3 Master 2, 12 undergrads)

PhD student

 Yara Santos Rodrigues Regulation and evolution of developmental plasticity in insect pigmentation: temperature and immunity interactions. (Co-supervision with Beldade P from Lisbon Univ.; 2015 - Oct. 2020)

• Master 2 students

- <u>Lafont P</u> A stochastic model for estimating immune parameters from the infection dynamics of a pathogen. (co-supervision with Ferdy JB (EDB, Toulouse Univ.); 2019)
- <u>Lemoine M</u> Ecological and evolutionary determinants of gut microbial communities in predatory insects. (Co-supervision with Zinger L (ENS Paris); 2017)
- o Mazana V Role of phenotypic switching in the division of labor during infection. (2017)

• Other undergraduate students

□ Lafont P (2018) □ Kardacz M (2017) □ Mazana V (2016) □ Kondolf H (2014, 2015) □ Ortiz G (2013 - 2015) □ Fox M (2012 - 2015) □ Chow C (2013) □ Edraki A (2013) □ Ruder L (2010) □ Eichin D (2009) □ Gygli S (2009) □ Hofer L (2009, 2010)

Scientific communications

• Invited talks (18)

2020:

- Seminar at the Institute of Biology Zoology, Freie Universität Berlin, 11/2020 (online talk; invited by Olivia Judson, Jens Rolf and Sophie Armitage)
- Seminar New voices in Infection Biology, Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology, Berlin, 10/2020 (online talk; invited by Igor Iatsenko) Recording at: https://youtu.be/e0N7eg-U0hI
- Seminar at Department DGIMI, Montpellier University, 10/2020 (online talk; invited by Alain Givaudan)

2019 and before:

- Innsbruck University, Innsbruck, Austria- 11/2019 (talk; invited by Markus Möst)
- Edinburgh University, Edinburgh, UK 06/2018 (talk; invited by Sarah Reece)
- o <u>EPFL</u>, Lausanne, Switzerland -04/2018 (talk; invited by Bruno Lemaitre)
- o University of Burgundy, Dijon, FR 12/2017(talk; invited by Thierry Rigaud)
- o University of Montpellier (SEEM), Montpellier, FR 12/2017(talk; invited by Karen McCoy)
- o <u>Insect Biology Research Institute</u>, Tours, FR 10/2017 (talk; invited by Joel Meunier)
- o CNRS, Gif-sur-Yvette, FR 04/2016 (talk; invited by Frédéric Mery)
- o Centre Biologie du Développement, Toulouse, FR 04/2016 (talk; invited by Alain Vincent)
- o Conference LabEx TULIP, Toulouse, FR 03/2016 (talk; invited by Etienne Danchin)
- o Institute for advanced study, Toulouse, FR 06/2015 (talk; invited by Arnaud Togneti)
- Seminar at the Center for infectious disease dynamics, PennState University, University Park,
 PA, USA 04/2014 (talk; invited by David Hughes)
- Seminar at the department of Evolution, Ecology and Genetics, Australian National University,
 Canberra, Australia 02/2014 (talk; invited by Hanna Kokko).
- Seminar at the department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Rochester University, Rochester, USA - 11/2013 (talk; invited by John Jaenike).
- Department of Evolutionary Biology of Cornell University, Ithaca, USA 2012 (talk)
- <u>Institute for Development Research</u> (IRD), Montpellier, FR 2010 (talk; invited by Karen McCoy)

• Conferences (15)

- o Conference ESEB (2nd joint congress), Montpellier, FR 08/2018 (Poster)
- <u>Conference Jacques Monod</u> "Open questions in ecology and evolution in infectious diseases: from fundamental research to evolutionary medicine" - Roscoff Biological Station, FR - 10/2017 (Poster)
- o Conference Immuninv2017, Lyon, FR 06/2017 (Contributed talk)
- o REID Annual Conference, Poitiers, FR 03/2016 (Contributed talk)
- o Conference 15thESEB, Lausanne, Switzerland 08/2015 (Contributed talk)
- <u>Conference Jacques Monod</u>, "Infectious diseases as drivers of evolution: the challenges ahead" -Roscoff Biological Station, FR - 09/2014 (contributed talk)
- o <u>Drosophila research conference</u>, San Diego, USA 03/2014 (poster)
- o Conference 14th ESEB, Lisbon, Portugal 08/2013 (poster)
- o <u>Drosophila research conference</u>, Washington DC, USA 03/2013 (poster)
- o Conference ESEB (joint congress), Ottawa, Canada 08/2012 (contributed talk)
- o Conference 13th ESEB, Tubingen, Germany 08/2011 (contributed talk)
- o Conference Swiss-Russian Seminar, Freiburg, Switzerland 2010 (contributed talk)
- o Conference 16th EMPSEB, Wierzba, Poland 2010 (contributed talk)
- o Conference 12 ESEB, Turin, Italy 2009 (contributed talk)
- o Conference 15th EMPSEB, Shoorl, Netherlands 2009 (contributed talk)

Scientific outreach

- What is CovID? (2020) Talk for primary school kids and their parents, online USA & online Italy
- De Dinechin D, Deguine JP, **Duneau D** (2006) *L'Homme de Florès. La découverte d'une nouvelle espèce humaine.* **Annales de la Société d'Horticulture et d'Histoire Naturelle de l'Hérault** 146 : 38-45
- Duneau D, Deguine JP, De Dinechin M, Blondel J (2006) L'homme de Flores. Nanisme et gigantisme insulaire. Annales de la Société d'Horticulture et d'Histoire Naturelle de l'Hérault 146: 57-66
- Deguine JP, De Dinechin M, Duneau D (2006) L'Homme de Florès. L'évolution de l'Homme et Homo floresiensis. Annales de la Société d'Horticulture et d'Histoire Naturelle de l'Hérault 146: 87-94
- o **Epidemiology Fact Sheets** Mosquito Biology for the Homeowner
- o Scientific documentary (52min) « Toto le nemato. », Price Buffon 2008 « Festival Paris science »